<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Owen Derby</title>
    <link>https://owenderby.com/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Owen Derby</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 00:44:37 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://owenderby.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Hosting my Personal Website (for Free!)</title>
      <link>https://owenderby.com/blog/website-setup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 00:44:37 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owenderby.com/blog/website-setup/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This website came about because I wanted to update my personal website and I had
some time on my hands. After reflection, I decided to build a static site and
host it with GitHub Pages. In retrospect, the process was mostly
straightforward, but there were a few points that weren&amp;rsquo;t obvious to me at the
time. This post details how I built the site, what I tools I ended up using, and
how the site is hosted, for free! Maybe you&amp;rsquo;ll find it helpful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;building-a-static-site&#34;&gt;Building a Static Site&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first decision I made was that I would use
a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Static_web_page&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;static site&lt;/a&gt;. I only wanted to
showcase my projects, host my resume, post the occasional blog post, and display
other static content. Any experimentation or fancy interactions I wanted would
most likely be in browser-side Javascript, so a static site would serve my needs
well. Going with a static website also meant I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t need to run my own
server (if I used a third-party hosting service), reducing my potential costs
significantly. Also, because there&amp;rsquo;s no database or server interactions, it
greatly reduces the attack surface, making it much easier to secure the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I needed to decide how to build the site. A simple search for &amp;ldquo;build a
static site&amp;rdquo; yields an array of tools and even more guides to the &amp;ldquo;10 best
static site generators&amp;rdquo;. There&amp;rsquo;s also a variety of managed solutions (like
Wordpress, Wix, Squarespace, etc.). Somewhat overwhelming to decide between, to
say the least. I knew I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to do it all from scratch (I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to
style it from scratch or co-opt existing themes), and I was trying to do this as
cheaply as possible, so that ruled out paying for managed solutions. That left
using an open source tool to build it&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But which tool to use?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wound up going with &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, because it was well-reviewed,
actively maintained, and written in Go. The documentation is decent (and it was
updated several times just while I was building the site) and the forum is
active, so &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/overview/quickstart/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;getting up and running&lt;/a&gt; was
relatively easy. The tool has quite a few configurations and built-in
integrations (like &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/extras/analytics/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/extras/comments/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Disqus integration&lt;/a&gt;), providing a lot
of functionality out of the box. There are also a bunch of
pre-built &lt;a href=&#34;http://themes.gohugo.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;themes&lt;/a&gt; to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One downside I encountered was how cumbersome it is to customize the site in
certain ways. Hugo is great if you everything you want to do fits well within
their existing configurations and exposed functionality (which, to be fair, is
quite expansive). However, if you want to customize anything outside of that,
like the layout of the blog posts page or styling content differently, it
requires diving much deeper into the internals of how Hugo organizes and builds
the site, just to figure out where the bit of logic exists that you want to
change. And then to change it, you need to figure out the local location to
place a file to contain the overriding/customized code. So there&amp;rsquo;s quite a step
function (in the learning curve) between just using the tool and customizing the
result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I&amp;rsquo;m glad I went with an existing solution, despite some of it&amp;rsquo;s
rough edges. I didn&amp;rsquo;t explore any other solutions, so I can&amp;rsquo;t say whether Hugo
was the best tool for me or not, but I&amp;rsquo;m happy with my choice. Although it took
more work to get the site I wanted than I anticipated, I know I got much
farther, quicker with Hugo than I would have on my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;hosting-and-serving-the-site&#34;&gt;Hosting and Serving the Site&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had my static site built, I needed to figure out where I&amp;rsquo;d host it. My
goals for hosting were that it be (1) as cheap as possible and (2) easy to
deploy to. Because it&amp;rsquo;s all static, I could host it on any of the existing file
storage services (e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/s3/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;S3&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/storage/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GCS&lt;/a&gt;). However, those would cost money
(likely less than $1 per month, but it&amp;rsquo;s the principle of the thing!), and I had
a hunch I could do it for free. Then I discovered you could host static websites
with &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. Free and integrated directly
into GitHub (so no extra deploy steps), Pages was clearly the way to go. The
only potential drawback was that my site and code would need to be public. Since
I was using open source tools and all my content was going to be public anyways,
this wasn&amp;rsquo;t a problem for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final piece was figuring out the domain I wanted to host the page at. GitHub
provides free subdomains on the github.io domain for all Pages, but I wanted a
custom domain to truly make the site mine. I had
used &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.name.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;name.com&lt;/a&gt; in the past, so I just used them to
register &lt;a href=&#34;https://owenderby.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;owenderby.com&lt;/a&gt; for $8.98 (including Whois
Privacy).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;gluing-everything-together&#34;&gt;Gluing Everything Together&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the major decisions made, it was time to assemble the parts and get the
site up. This was accomplished in the following steps/configurations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Hugo to create the initial site: &lt;code&gt;hugo new site .&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/themes/installing/#installing-a-specific-theme&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Install a Hugo theme&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/themes/usage/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;set it as default&lt;/a&gt; for the site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build the site in the docs directory (this is important for hosting with
GitHub Pages in step 5): &lt;code&gt;hugo -d docs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a git repository, commit the initial site and push it up to GitHub.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup GitHub Pages to work for a custom domain. You need to follow
a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/articles/using-a-custom-domain-with-github-pages/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;few directions&lt;/a&gt; to
do this, including setting up DNS entries and configuring the repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final step I took was setting up TLS (HTTPS) for my site. Although not
strictly required, I generally expect all sites I use these days to be served
over TLS, so my site couldn&amp;rsquo;t be an exception. Sadly, GitHub Pages doesn&amp;rsquo;t
support HTTPS for custom
domains. Fortunately, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cloudflare.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Cloudflare&lt;/a&gt; provides a free
plan for personal websites, which includes their Full SSL solution via shared
certificates, so you can simply sign up for a free account and setup
SSL. Cloudflare has a
good
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.cloudflare.com/secure-and-fast-github-pages-with-cloudflare/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; covering
how to do this with GitHub Pages, so I just followed the directions there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there you go! For the cost of registering a domain name, you have your own
personal static website up and served on your custom domain! And of course,
you could do this all for free if you were satisfied with hosting it on the
GitHub domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit (April 6 2016):&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;I also setup gmail for owenderby.com using Mailgun,
all for free. Rather than repeat the steps here, you can follow
this
&lt;a href=&#34;https://simplyian.com/2015/01/07/Hacking-GMail-to-use-custom-domains-for-free/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;guide&lt;/a&gt; to
do it yourself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;What kind of developer would I be if I didn&amp;rsquo;t build it myself? (And before
you roll your eyes, at least I didn&amp;rsquo;t build it from scratch!)&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making Panoramas</title>
      <link>https://owenderby.com/blog/panoramas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 17:23:05 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owenderby.com/blog/panoramas/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I recently finished up a month of travel. In addition to seeing great friends
and beautiful places, I used my travels as an opportunity to learn how to use a
DSLR. I mean &lt;em&gt;really learn&lt;/em&gt;, beyond just the point-and-shoot basics we all
know. So I borrowed an old Nikon D40 from a friend and sort of just dove
in. Turns out, it&amp;rsquo;s not very difficult to go from n00b to novice, and it&amp;rsquo;s even
easier to take a lot of photos&amp;hellip;but that&amp;rsquo;s a story for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/pano_sample.jpg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/pano_sample.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A lovely creek in Boise National
Forest.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;/p&gt;
      
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the challenges I (unwittingly) set for myself was creating panoramas,
like the one above. It seems straightforward in theory - shoot a series of
overlapping photos and then combine them using software. Afterall, most modern
smart phones have panorama modes built into their camera apps. However, as I
soon learned, it can very easily turn into a deep, interesting &lt;del&gt;trap&lt;/del&gt; rabbit
hole of techniques and details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is a summary of my findings from figuring out how to create panoramas
from individual photos, and then uploading them to Facebook as &amp;ldquo;Photo
Spheres&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t as simple as I expected it to be, so I wanted to
record my insights and process, for my future self and anyone else who is silly
enough to try for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last aside - I work predominantly on Ubuntu with FOSS, so this is written
using entirely open source tools. This is definitely possible using Photoshop
(heck, it&amp;rsquo;s probably much easier), but YMMV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-the-panorama&#34;&gt;Making the Panorama&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s effectively two components to my process:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol type=&#34;A&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Produce the raw panorama by stitching together a series of pictures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the panorama to have the correct field of view (FOV) and image size and
   then add appropriate metadata so it&#39;s recognized as a Photo Sphere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section focuses on part A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;taking-the-photos&#34;&gt;Taking the Photos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&#39;row&#39;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#39;col-xs-6 col-sm-3&#39;&gt;
        &lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/a.JPG&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/a.JPG&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#39;col-xs-6 col-sm-3&#39;&gt;
        &lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/b.JPG&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/b.JPG&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#39;col-xs-6 col-sm-3&#39;&gt;
        &lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/c.JPG&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/c.JPG&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#39;col-xs-6 col-sm-3&#39;&gt;
        &lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/d.JPG&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/d.JPG&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#39;caption&#39;&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;4 individuals photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I was just starting out with a borrowed camera, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t very
sophisticated in my setup for taking the panorama shots. I shot hand-held, and
used the horizon as my reference as I swept my camera across the scene, taking
pictures periodically. Of course, there are
some &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.panotools.org/Heads&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;very fancy rigs&lt;/a&gt; out there to buy for
your tripod, and there are even some clever techniques for better hand-held
shots (google &amp;ldquo;philopod&amp;rdquo; if you&amp;rsquo;re curious).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I found I was able to produce decent panoramas, once I learned how
to keep the exposure and white balance the same in every picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;ProTip #1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; – Consider using
the &lt;a href=&#34;https://photographylife.com/nikon-ae-l-af-l-button&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;AutoExposure-Lock&lt;/a&gt;
feature of your camera when taking a photo series for a panorama. It makes the
resulting panorama look more natural and contiguous, at the cost of some
places potentially being under- or over-exposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t have many problems with parallax, since I was taking mostly wide-angle
landscape panoramas. But I now know that I can reduce parallax effects by
rotating the camera about
its &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.panotools.org/No-parallax_point&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;no-parallax point&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stitching-the-photos&#34;&gt;Stitching the Photos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For stitching, the best open source tool I found&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
is &lt;a href=&#34;http://hugin.sourceforge.net/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Hugin&lt;/a&gt;. Hugin is actually a front end GUI for
the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.panotools.org/Panorama_tools&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Panorama Tools&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Hugin is an amazing tool and can be used to do a tremendous amount of
things. And so, here is where the hole really starts. Between trying to figure
out how to use the tool and being distracted by learning what people do with the
tool, I spent way too long here. And every time I revisit this, I seem to lose
more time&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But, even I have limits to how deep down the rabbit hole I&amp;rsquo;ll
go. So, here I&amp;rsquo;ll be focusing on the practical findings, and leaving some
questions unanswered&amp;hellip;because&amp;hellip;I just need to move on 😵&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, without further adieu, here&amp;rsquo;s the CliffsNotes&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for creating panoramas in
Hugin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Load you photo series.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch to &amp;lsquo;Advanced&amp;rsquo; interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the &amp;lsquo;Photos&amp;rsquo; tab:

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select &amp;lsquo;Hugin\&amp;rsquo;s CPFind + Celeste&amp;rsquo; option for Feature Matching. Press
&amp;lsquo;Create control points&amp;rsquo; button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select &amp;lsquo;Positions, View and Barrel&amp;rsquo; for Geometric.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the optimizer (Edit &amp;gt; Optimize)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch back to &amp;lsquo;Simple&amp;rsquo; interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &amp;lsquo;Preview&amp;rsquo; tab and review panorama. You&amp;rsquo;re looking for a few things:

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are there any redundant photos? (e.g. photos arranged [1][2][3] such
that 1 and 3 have enough overlap that 2 isn&amp;rsquo;t needed).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are there any moving objects (cars, people) in the image? If so, consider
using a &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.panotools.org/Hugin_Mask_tab&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;mask&lt;/a&gt; to hide it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the panorama look good (well aligned and not distorted)? If not, you
may need to manually
add/remove
&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.panotools.org/Hugin_Control_Points_tab&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;control points&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the &amp;lsquo;Projection&amp;rsquo; tab and press the &amp;lsquo;Fit&amp;rsquo; button. You may want to try
different projections to see if any work better. For wide-angle panoramas of
nature, &amp;lsquo;cylindrical&amp;rsquo; seems best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the &amp;lsquo;Move/Drag&amp;rsquo; tab and press &amp;lsquo;Straighten&amp;rsquo; button. This should make a
very subtle change to the panorama - if instead it turns your panorama into
an &amp;rsquo;S&amp;rsquo;, Hugin probably has your lens information or focal length wrong&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/int_pano_hugin.jpg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/int_pano_hugin.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;
        Panorama so far.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Okay, so now you have a choice, depending on what sort of panorama you want to
produce. Typically, you&amp;rsquo;ll want to produce a Photo Sphere, which is a much
cooler way to show off your panorama. In that case, proceed to the
next &lt;a href=&#34;#make-sphere&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;section&lt;/a&gt; now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, sometimes you just want a flat, cropped panorama. I typically opt for
this when the estimated horizontal FOV&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is ≤160° or I&amp;rsquo;m just stitching
together a couple photos (not really a panorama). To do this, we continue from
above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch to &amp;lsquo;Advanced&amp;rsquo; interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &amp;lsquo;Stitcher&amp;rsquo; tab and&amp;hellip;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &amp;lsquo;Calculate Optimal Size&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &amp;lsquo;Fit Crop to Images&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure &amp;lsquo;Exposure corrected, low dynamic range&amp;rsquo; is the only option selected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the format to &amp;lsquo;JPEG&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &amp;lsquo;Stitch!&amp;rsquo; button and choose place to save hugin project file, then
name and place to save resulting panorama.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/flat_pano.jpg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/flat_pano.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;
        Finished flat panorama.
      &lt;/p&gt;
      
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it - you should have a nice, clear panorama to post as you like!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;make-sphere&#34;&gt;Making a Photo Sphere&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, you might want to post your panorama as a Photo Sphere. To do so, you
just need to massage it into a size and shape that Facebook will accept and
recognize as a 360° image&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;image-shape&#34;&gt;Image Shape&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you need to make your panorama fit into one of seven predefined sizes
(determined by horizontal and vertical FOV):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Go back to the &amp;lsquo;Projection&amp;rsquo; tab and note the estimated horizontal and
vertical FOV values. Then find the row in the following table that best
matches those values. Enter the FOV values from the table into Hugin. The
Image Size and Command you&amp;rsquo;ll use next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;H FOV&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;V FOV&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Image Size (px)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Command&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;120°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;86°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6000x5343&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;text&#34; class=&#34;form-control input-sm&#34; value=&#34;exiftool -overwrite_original -FullPanoWidthPixels=18000 -FullPanoHeightPixels=9000 -CroppedAreaLeftPixels=6000 -CroppedAreaTopPixels=2350 -CroppedAreaImageWidthPixels=6000 -CroppedAreaImageHeightPixels=4300 -ProjectionType=cylindrical path/to/image.jpg&#34; readonly=&#34;&#34; onclick=&#34;this.select()&#34;&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;150°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;86°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6000x4274&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;text&#34; class=&#34;form-control input-sm&#34; value=&#34;exiftool -overwrite_original -FullPanoWidthPixels=14400 -FullPanoHeightPixels=7200 -CroppedAreaLeftPixels=4200 -CroppedAreaTopPixels=1880 -CroppedAreaImageWidthPixels=6000 -CroppedAreaImageHeightPixels=3440 -ProjectionType=cylindrical path/to/image.jpg&#34; readonly=&#34;&#34; onclick=&#34;this.select()&#34;&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;180°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;86°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6000x3562&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;text&#34; class=&#34;form-control input-sm&#34; value=&#34;exiftool -overwrite_original -FullPanoWidthPixels=12000 -FullPanoHeightPixels=6000 -CroppedAreaLeftPixels=3000 -CroppedAreaTopPixels=1567 -CroppedAreaImageWidthPixels=6000 -CroppedAreaImageHeightPixels=2867 -ProjectionType=cylindrical path/to/image.jpg&#34; readonly=&#34;&#34; onclick=&#34;this.select()&#34;&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;240°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;86°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6000x2671&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;text&#34; class=&#34;form-control input-sm&#34; value=&#34;exiftool -overwrite_original -FullPanoWidthPixels=9000 -FullPanoHeightPixels=4500 -CroppedAreaLeftPixels=1500 -CroppedAreaTopPixels=1175 -CroppedAreaImageWidthPixels=6000 -CroppedAreaImageHeightPixels=2150 -ProjectionType=cylindrical path/to/image.jpg&#34; readonly=&#34;&#34; onclick=&#34;this.select()&#34;&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;300°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;86°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6000x2137&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;text&#34; class=&#34;form-control input-sm&#34; value=&#34;exiftool -overwrite_original -FullPanoWidthPixels=7200 -FullPanoHeightPixels=3600 -CroppedAreaLeftPixels=600 -CroppedAreaTopPixels=940 -CroppedAreaImageWidthPixels=6000 -CroppedAreaImageHeightPixels=1720 -ProjectionType=cylindrical path/to/image.jpg&#34; readonly=&#34;&#34; onclick=&#34;this.select()&#34;&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;360°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;86°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6000x1781&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;text&#34; class=&#34;form-control input-sm&#34; value=&#34;exiftool -overwrite_original -FullPanoWidthPixels=6000 -FullPanoHeightPixels=3000 -CroppedAreaLeftPixels=0 -CroppedAreaTopPixels=783 -CroppedAreaImageWidthPixels=6000 -CroppedAreaImageHeightPixels=1433 -ProjectionType=cylindrical path/to/image.jpg&#34; readonly=&#34;&#34; onclick=&#34;this.select()&#34;&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;360°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;65°&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6000x1217&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=&#34;text&#34; class=&#34;form-control input-sm&#34; value=&#34;exiftool -overwrite_original -FullPanoWidthPixels=6000 -FullPanoHeightPixels=3000 -CroppedAreaLeftPixels=0 -CroppedAreaTopPixels=958 -CroppedAreaImageWidthPixels=6000 -CroppedAreaImageHeightPixels=1083 -ProjectionType=cylindrical path/to/image.jpg&#34; readonly=&#34;&#34; onclick=&#34;this.select()&#34;&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Go to the &amp;lsquo;Crop&amp;rsquo; tab and click on the button next to the crop dimensions to
&amp;lsquo;reset crop to maximal possible area&amp;rsquo;. The result should be your panorama
embedded in an overall image which covers the desired FOV.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Switch back to &amp;lsquo;Advanced&amp;rsquo; interface.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Go to &amp;lsquo;Stitcher&amp;rsquo; tab and&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the Canvas Width to be 6000. The Height value should match the Image
Size given in the above table. Leave all other values for FOV and Crop
alone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure &amp;lsquo;Exposure corrected, low dynamic range&amp;rsquo; is the only option selected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the format to &amp;lsquo;JPEG&amp;rsquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press &amp;lsquo;Stitch!&amp;rsquo; button and choose place to save hugin project file, then
name and place to save resulting panorama.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should result in something that looks like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/flat_photosphere.jpg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/flat_photosphere.jpg&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
      
      &lt;p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Photosphere (shown as
regular image, so appears flat).&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;/p&gt;
      
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;image-metadata&#34;&gt;Image Metadata&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you need to set the metadata correctly on your image so that it &lt;em&gt;declares&lt;/em&gt;
itself as a Photo Sphere. This can be done with
the &lt;a href=&#34;http://owl.phy.queensu.ca/~phil/exiftool/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;exiftool&lt;/a&gt; command line
tool. You&amp;rsquo;ll notice in the table above I&amp;rsquo;ve provided the appropriate commands to
run for each FOV. Copy the appropriate command and run it in your terminal&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:13&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Be
sure to replace &lt;code&gt;path/to/image.jpg&lt;/code&gt; with the appropriate path to your image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;uploading-to-facebook&#34;&gt;Uploading to Facebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally! You&amp;rsquo;re ready to upload to facebook&amp;hellip;or are you? Well, you are, but
Facebook imposes the following restrictions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can only upload to the web (desktop) version of Facebook&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip; and you have to post it directly to your timeline (you can&amp;rsquo;t add it to an
album directly&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:14&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip; and you can only upload one panorama at a time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you follow all those steps, then it should totally work and you will end up
with an awesome Photo Sphere to share with all your friends.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/oderby/posts/10154843778091522&#34;&gt;
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://owenderby.com/img/panos/fb_photosphere.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Click to view the photosphere on Facebook.&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Click to view the photosphere on Facebook.
        
            
        
        &lt;/p&gt; 
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-directions&#34;&gt;Future Directions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it! I hope if you made it this far you found this guide useful, or at
least insightful&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have time, I&amp;rsquo;d like to investigate the following areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigate how to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bracketing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;bracketing&lt;/a&gt;
to get a better overall exposure for the panoramas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is lens &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vignetting&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;vignette&lt;/a&gt;, and do I
need to correct/remove it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I find the max 6000 pixel photo size imposed by facebook to be limiting. So
I&amp;rsquo;d like to investigate ways to provide my own 360° photo viewer, using
three.js. &lt;a href=&#34;https://threejs.org/examples/?q=panorama#webgl_panorama_equirectangular&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; looks
promising.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;Technically, a panorama using a spherical projection for viewing. Google calls these &amp;ldquo;Photo Spheres&amp;rdquo;, and that&amp;rsquo;s the term I&amp;rsquo;ll use. However, Facebook calls them &lt;a href=&#34;https://facebook360.fb.com/360-photos/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;360° photos&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I dislike this term because they&amp;rsquo;re not always 360° (in particular, for most panoramas you want to take with your DSLR.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Alright, the only one I found that I actually tried. But after further searching, it seems to actually be the best one out there.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;I just fell, again, into the deep &lt;del&gt;trap&lt;/del&gt; rabbit hole again figuring out where to point to for a good summary document here&amp;hellip;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Yes, that is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CliffsNotes&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;correct spelling&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;This is an area that, despite several attempts, I haven&amp;rsquo;t fully figured out yet. The focal length and other important lens information is always present in the photo EXIF data, but for some reason Hugin typically inputs some different values for focal length and focal length multiplier (crop factor), and I haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out why yet. Typically, just leaving those alone seems fine, but if my panorama isn&amp;rsquo;t aligning properly, I&amp;rsquo;ll try putting in the exact values from the EXIF data, and that does the trick.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;This is another area I don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand - how does Hugin estimate the field of view for the resulting panorama?? I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure the math is outlined &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.panotools.org/DSLR_spherical_resolution&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but I think that article is a bit muddled&amp;hellip;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;For uploading to Facebook. Although the result should work with any other Photo Sphere renderer, I haven&amp;rsquo;t tested it.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;This was an especially infuriating endeavor, as Facebook has &lt;a href=&#34;https://facebook360.fb.com/editing-360-photos-injecting-metadata/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;detailed documentation&lt;/a&gt; on how to do it, but it&amp;rsquo;s focused mostly on producing 360° Photo Spheres using Photoshop. It took a lot of trial and error to figure out how to make it work for partial Photo Spheres.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;For the curious, this command specifies how to place our partial panorama inside a full spherical panorama (360° x 180°). See &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/streetview/spherical-metadata#metadata_properties&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for further details and a nice illustration. The astute will observe that this is redundant with the work we already did to fit our original panorama into one of the predefined FOV Facebook specifies&amp;hellip;and all I can say is &amp;ldquo;Yes. Don&amp;rsquo;t ask.&amp;rdquo;
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;Instead, you can move a photo from your timeline to an album. Just open the image, then go to Options &amp;gt; &amp;lsquo;Move to Other Album&amp;rsquo;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://owenderby.com/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2016 22:55:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owenderby.com/projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;section id=&#34;projects&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Projects&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;panel panel-default&#34;&gt;
      &lt;div class=&#34;panel-body&#34;&gt;
      &lt;h5&gt;
        &lt;i class=&#34;fa
        fa-github&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/oderby/elections_2016&#34;&gt;
        elections_2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - A scratchpad for my data dives into
        presidential election data.
      &lt;/h5&gt;
      &lt;h5&gt;
        &lt;i class=&#34;fa
        fa-github&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/oderby/owenderby.com&#34;&gt;
        owenderby.com &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - The source code for this website. It&#39;s
        self-referential!
      &lt;/h5&gt;

      &lt;h5&gt;
        &lt;i class=&#34;fa
        fa-table&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/19VmJKOBl8GthIXbXeaV4Mo-613QZuxSeYxObE3XPiMM/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;
        2017 Cabinet Confirmation Tracker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - A spreadsheet I threw
        together to track confirmation of Trump&#39;s nominees in Jan 2017.
      &lt;/h5&gt;
      &lt;h5&gt;
        &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-github&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/oderby/cmap2d&#34;&gt;cmap2d&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        - A small library for generating and sampling 2D RGB colormaps.
      &lt;/h5&gt;
      &lt;h5&gt;
        &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-github&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mitpokerbots/pbots_calc&#34;&gt;pbots_calc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
        - An open-source poker hand equity calculator library, written in C with
        bindings for C and Java. Available for PC, Mac and Linux.
      &lt;/h5&gt;

      &lt;!-- &lt;h5&gt; --&gt;
      &lt;!--   &lt;i class=&#34;fa fa-github&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; --&gt;
      &lt;!--   &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#&#34;&gt;Project 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - Description. --&gt;
      &lt;!-- &lt;/h5&gt; --&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://owenderby.com/resume/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://owenderby.com/resume/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;+++ date = &amp;ldquo;2016-11-05T21:05:33+05:30&amp;rdquo; title = &amp;ldquo;About me&amp;rdquo; +++&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>